we continue now with our brief survey of
the Enlightenment we asked the question
now why was the Enlightenment
called the enlightenment
what was the new light that was being
shed on on issues of the day
well the 18th century Enlightenment
perhaps more than any period in the
history of Western thought
showed a spirit of unbridled optimism
with respect to the progress of the mind
or what we might call intellectual
progress we've seen the startling
results in science and now revolutions
occurring around the world and new
paradigms for government with freedom
and individual responsibility and these
things that are taking place the
enlightenment brought with it a severe
tension
between philosophy and the church
because for many of the thinkers of the
Enlightenment
it was the church that was seen as the
chief impediment or obstacle to further
philosophical Improvement and
intellectual progress
because the church was bound up in her
dogmatism and was perceived by many of
the critics of the Enlightenment to be
the enemy of free thinking and free
investigation for truth wherever it
could be found
and so we see this critique emerge
against the church and against
Christianity now one of the most
important figures of the Enlightenment
was the French philosopher Voltaire
and Voltaire was very critical of the
church but he was not critical of theism
he was a devout believer in God
and his problem as he said was he was
not struggling against faith
but against superstition
not even against religion
but against the institutional church as
he encountered it in his day
see we wanted to leave room for Faith
and so he was he was somewhat critical
of uh
of religion but his basic Target was the
church
and particularly uh the the the the
Protestant church at that day that it
followed after Calvin and and Luther and
and he was also very critical of Pascal
because of Pascal's Revival of
augustinian thought within the Roman
Catholic Community
and Voltaire didn't like that he shared
voltaire's
a concern for human corruption but he
he saw more of the problem with
superstition
and and an uninformed unintellectual
approach to Faith but I would say the
Voltaire is more of a a literary figure
a kind of a transitional figure here
where he was a moderate with respect to
his critique of religion the French
encyclopedia encyclopedists were the
avowed enemies of all religion and they
were the ones people like the hobok and
diedero who declared themselves personal
enemies of God
and brought forth the basic theme of the
Enlightenment which was this namely that
the god hypothesis
is no longer necessary
to explain all of the old philosophical
and historical problems such as where
did the world come from what is the
origin of human life now science apart
from the Bible and apart from religion
can answer all those questions that
earlier philosophers had to fall back
upon their speculation on the first
cause as God to explain the world as we
find it so again let me say that what
they would would condense their view of
Enlightenment was that where the lights
came on was to the realization
that God is not a necessary hypothesis
for theoretical thought
now these men
in their efforts to put aside all forms
of theism
develop the idea of spontaneous
generation
as the alternative to the Christian
concept of creation
which view at that time seemed to be
credible within the scientific world but
under later
examination was found to be completely
absurd spontaneous generation means that
things just pop into existence out of
nothing
now
for a short period of time
there were efforts in the enlightenment
to produce a natural religion
natural religion
which would be a religion based upon
reason
and a religion that would be noted for
its Chief article of tolerance or
toleration
by the 18th century Europe was fed up
with religious Warfare
with the endless disputes between
Protestants and Roman Catholics and all
of the pain and suffering that had gone
on in the world as a result of these
Fierce theological controversies
and so religion was upsetting daily life
and of course these people thought that
it was also a barrier towards a greater
Awakening or illumination that we can
find through Natural Science one of the
ironies of this of course is that while
this is going on in Europe in the 18th
century
what's going on in America in the
colonies
is the Great Awakening
with the work of Jonathan Edwards and
Whitfield and Wesley and the biggest
religious revival that this new world
would have experienced not only up to
that point but since that point
and while religion is taking off in full
force in America
it's it's suffering calamitous
consequences under the impact of the
Enlightenment in Europe
now for a time being
for a short period of time the new
religion
that sought to replace classical
Christianity on the continent was the
religion of deism I've mentioned this in
passing before
because of its historical significance
the deists were those who still Affirmed
the existence of God they still believe
that reason demanded God as Creator
Voltaire for example was convinced that
reason demonstrated compellingly the
need for a necessary being and followed
Descartes at that point
but
they wanted to strip religion
of all of the accretions that have been
heaped upon it through the history of
the church
and get back to the basics of natural
religion the religion by which God
reveals himself in nature
so natural religion supplants biblical
religion
and here is we here's where we find the
initial stages of radical criticism
being offered against the Integrity of
the scriptures because there's an
all-out effort by the Enlightenment
thinkers to get rid of the authority of
the scriptures now that also according
to experts on this period was motivated
in large measure
by the resistance against augustinian
Theology and against the doctrine of
original sin
I mean there was a tacid agreement that
Luther Calvin Augustine and so on that
the reformers were right about the
condition of man's fallenness
and that they that they had the Bible on
their side over against erasmus's higher
view of man and against all pelagian
forms of theology
so rather than try to ground their
anti-augestinianism on a different
interpretation of the Bible they decided
to do what get rid of the Bible and look
at our understanding of Mankind through
the eyes of nature so you see all kinds
of philosophies emerging in the 18th
century
extolling the virtue and the innocence
of man in nature which reaches its uh
its Supreme expression in the work of
Rousseau but in any case
that what the Enlightenment thinkers are
seeking first of all is a natural
religion that is marked by toleration
and it gets the name of theism
and deism is a particular form of theism
that still says that God creates the
world but he basically steps back out of
the world and lets the world operate
according to the fixed natural laws that
he has imbued into the creation
and God doesn't intervene in the
structure of human events now of course
as an organized religion
deism had a very short lifespan
so it was just simply a blip on the
radar screen of Western history but I've
also said many times
that even though it passed away quickly
the ongoing consequences of it reached
down even to today
and there were those in the colonies who
were practicing Dias and their
contribution to the formation of the
ideals of the American governmental
system is a matter of much debate and so
on
but that they were engaged in it and
that they were real is beyond dispute
but in any case you have things in the
Declaration of Independence that speaks
about we are endowed by our creator with
certain inalienable rights okay
and or later on we hold these truths to
be self-evident the language of that
kind of documentation
is language that comes right out of this
environment of the 18th century which
was an attempt to base government and
religion on nature
this is also the Heyday of natural law
now
the medieval Church believed in natural
law Saint Thomas Aquinas was a great
advocate of natural law but the natural
law theorists of Christian history took
their cue from the biblical exposition
of natural law because Paul for example
in Romans 2 speaks about the law of God
that is written on our hearts that not
only do we learn God's law from
listening to Moses and the Ten
Commandments and so on but we also have
conscience and we also have an innate
understanding of right and wrong this is
the kind of thing that Emmanuel Kant
labors with with respect to his view of
ethics
but that is the natural law or The Lex
materialis was seen by the classical
Christian synthesis as
a reflection in this world of the
so-called Lex I turnitatus or the
Eternal law of God
so that natural law was a consistent
application of biblical law
what's going on now in the 18th century
Enlightenment is an attempt to
de-supernaturalize life these
supernaturalized religion if you will
so that the Bible has to go
and
Supernatural revealed theology has to go
and in its place comes natural theology
or natural religion
and this is a very important point to
understand because part of the
hostility in our own day against Natural
theology is rooted in the church's
awareness that it was The Advocates of
natural theology who gave birth to this
critique of revelation of the Bible and
all the rest I for example am an
outspoken advocate of the Reconstruction
of natural theology but not in the
enlightenment sense where you reduce
Christianity to what can be learned
simply through a study of nature but
rather
more in terms of the classical synthesis
as Aquinas had it where natural theology
simply reinforced what was already
present in the scripture now in any case
deism was welcomed by the moderates of
the Enlightenment
but the radicals of the Enlightenment
people like as I said dietero and the
French encyclopedists saw
deism as a fatal compromise with
religion in fact dietero said that what
D is a managed to accomplish in the
positive note was that it cut off 10
heads of the Hydra of of organized
religion
going back to the ancient mythology of
the Hydra you know what you cut off
ahead and grow too and so on this one
cut off 10 heads
but he said theism left that one head
the head of deism
and Dieter Rose said as long as that one
head is left all the other heads will
come back they'll all grow back and
we'll have all the same religious
problems in the future that we had in
the past and so
data Rowe was not satisfied with this
compromise
he wanted to take the ax to the root of
the tree or really to take the ax to the
neck and cut off all of the heads of
Hydra including the head of deism and uh
and get rid of religion altogether
now
Rousseau is one who was very important
in this period because
he also
fought against the classical Christian
view of original sin
and having rejected the biblical view of
mankind Russo came to the conclusion and
you've heard the famous statements man
is Born Free and everywhere he is in
Chains
I said again man is Born Free and
everywhere he is in Chains
now the real change that he's out to uh
to conquer are the chains
of original sin
that doctrine of original sin that again
was recovered by Pascal and others in
his own day and Russo wanted to granted
he agreed that there was much corruption
in humanity and society and civilization
in the 18th century according to Russo
was decadent
and because of the obvious Corruption of
human institutions
which the reformers would point to as
proof of the truth of original sin Let
me just add a comment uh parenthetically
Edwards over in America wrote his
masterful treaties on original sin in
the 18th century and he argued for the
doctrine of original sin not only
exegetically which he did do re showing
the biblical case for original sin but
he also has a lengthy section in his
treaties on original sin proved by
natural reason
and again to simplify this what Edwards
was saying was if the Bible didn't tell
us anything about a historical fall
or anything about the doctrine of
original sin
pure unvarnished reason would have to
construct a theory of original sin to
account for the universality of
corruption and that all people
everywhere struggle with sin
if we're all born
neutral
and not Fallen one would expect not to
find this kind of universality of human
corruption
so it's that kind of issue that Rousseau
was struggling with and he then gave his
description of what he called the human
state of nature
sort of like the innocent Savage we were
all born free from any kind of original
sin but then he was faced with this
question if we were all born
uh uh free of original sin
and born actually in a virtuous safe
State
why is the world so corrupt why is
society decadent well the answer that
Rousseau gave obviously was
that is the result
of government
man is born
with a a basic virtuous sense of
self-love which is not evil
but self-love degenerates into
selfishness
in community
when
governments come
and form established institutions
that sort of codify and place in
concrete the worst impulses of human
nature
for example one of the insights that
Russo had about this is
the interdependency of human beings on
each other the whole world functions on
the basis of a division of labor no man
is truly an island no man is ever really
self-sufficient the farmer needs the
Cattlemen for his meat and the and the
Cattleman needs the farmer for his wheat
and so on and we all are interdependent
in a global village on each other's
contributions to the human Enterprise
but as soon as I enter into a contract
with you or as soon as I enter into a
Cooperative Venture with you I become to
some degree dependent upon you
and the more dependent I am upon you
the more I expose myself to your impulse
to tyrannize me
so that the mutual relationships
tend toward tyranny
and the more
institutionalized these things become
the more government you have
then the more you are exploited and you
become alienated from your basic human
nature
we call it the rat race
and we most of us spend little time
thinking about how our lives are made
Complicated by the structures and the
systems of civilization and of society
as we know it
I mean we've sort of dropped into the
society in which we live and everybody's
expected to have a car if you don't have
a car there's something wrong with you
or you can't compete and
and you're expected to do this and
you're expected to do that and all the
while Big Brothers watching you and
hurting you and hurting herd not hurting
although they may do that too and so
Russo came the conclusion that every
person
becomes
whatever
the government
makes it
so that it is organized government that
corrupts individuals
you would think on the basis of this
that he would then
uh
appeal to a complete withdrawal from
society but that's not the case
instead what he needs that is what we
need is a whole new understanding of
government
where the government is based on a
social contract
on a covenant
between those who are ruled and those
who are the rulers and that Covenant is
spelled out in terms of just laws
and the just laws reflect the general
will or the general welfare and
everybody then by pulling for the
general good and for the general welfare
will be actually advancing their own
human interests and it's that kind of
thinking that brought about the French
Revolution that kind of thinking that
had an enormous impact on the
establishment of America and not don't
get me wrong I'm not opposed to the idea
of a social contract but I think it's
not even extreme to think that
government is going to cure the problems
of mankind the obvious question you
asked Russo is if if man is all
basically virtuous and it's civilization
that corrupts him
how did the civilization get corrupt in
the first place
because the civilization is simply
Society is simply made up of individuals
and
so that it's he's got the card before
the horse I think it doesn't really ever
answer the problem of the universality
of human sin except in a very naive way
but the upshot of all of this is a brand
new
uh sense of all right we have a new
illumination we're enlightened we can
now create our own destiny get out from
under the tyranny of the church and the
tyranny of monarchs and form a
government that is based upon mutual
agreement
the consent of the governed
where there are checks and balances in
place
and that will bring about a just Society
well we can look back at that and smile
because we still struggle with the
problems of decadence and moral
corruption and so on
and but now we do it so-called as
enlightened people
well not all the philosophers of that
day agreed with this somewhat optimistic
view of what natural reason would be
able to bring about or natural religion
or natural law
but rather became more and more
skeptical and more and more pessimistic
as they entered into the 19th century